[English subtitles are available]
[본 영상은 한글자막을 제공합니다]
[The Science of Falling in Love]
[이과생추입정망 : 사랑의 늪에 빠진 이과생]
[Episode 7]
[제7화]
What a busy day.
다들 바쁘네
Everyone,
잠깐 하던 일
listen to me.
그만하고
I have something to tell you.
제 말 들어요
As you know,
알다시피
our lab has been cooperating
우리 실험실은
with the First Affiliated Hospital
동남과기대
of Southeast Science
제일부속병원과
and Technology University
임상 분야의
in clinical applications.
협력을 이어왔어요
Tomorrow
내일
we will conduct a double check
환자 한 명을 대상으로
on a patient.
검사를 할 거야
I personally think that
개인적인 생각인데
for many members
이번 기회는
in our lab,
우리 실험실의
this is a very good opportunity
학생들한텐
to learn and understand.
학습할 좋은 기회예요
So in principle,
그래서
it is best not to ask for leave.
최대한 결석하지 않는 게 좋아요
The genetic engineering laboratory next door
유전자공학 실험실도
will also visit with us
이번에 같이 가서
this time.
참관할 거예요
Genetic engineering?
유전자공학?
Gu Chen's laboratory.
구천이 있는 실험실이네
Let’s gather at the East Gate of the school
내일  오전 8시 반에
on time at 8:30 tomorrow morning,
학교 동문 쪽에서 집합하는 거
shall we?
어때요?
-No problem. - No problem.
- 네 - 네
Get to work.
그럼 하던 일 마저 해요
[Southeast Science and Technology University]
[동남과학기술대학]
The recovery of the patient
환자의 상황이
goes well,
많이 호전되었어요
and there is basically no rejection.
거부반응도 없고
That’s good.
다행이네요
Today we are here
오늘은 환자분의
mainly to review
건강 상태를
the patient's recovery.
확인해 보려고 왔어요
In addition, several media
일부 언론사에서
have been inviting interviews.
인터뷰하고 싶다고 연락이 왔는데
Ms. Chen, to be honest,
솔직히
I am a little nervous today,
오늘은 조금 긴장되네요
because all the exoskeletons
환자의
of the patient
모든 외골격은
have to be controlled
자신의 뇌신경을 통해
by his own brain nerves.
통제해야 하니까요
Hope everything goes well.
모든 게 잘되길 바라네요
Take it easy.
긴장하지 마세요
-Please. - Please.
-이쪽으로 오시죠 - 자
Please.
이쪽으로 들어오세요
Today's focus is on items two and four.
오늘은 중점적으로 두 가지를 확인해 볼게요
Okay.
네
Step one, motor imagery.
일단 운동하는 상상을 해볼게요
Grandpa.
할아버지
Visualize in your mind
머릿속으로
which leg to take first
어느 쪽 다리를 먼저
and how to get to
내밀어야
the edge of the table.
책상 쪽으로 갈 수 있을까요?
Very good.
잘하셨습니다
Step two, grab action.
다음은 손으로 물건 들기입니다
Grandpa.
할아버지
Try to grab this soy milk cup.
이 종이컵을 한번 들어보세요
Take it easy, grandpa.
긴장하지 마세요, 할아버지
Just like our usual training.
평소 재활 운동할 때처럼
Lift it up.
위로 들어 올리세요
Right.
맞아요
No worries.
급해하지 마세요
Take it easy. Slow down.
긴장하지 마시고 천천히 하세요
No worries. Slow down.
급해하지 말고 천천히요
Great.
잘하셨습니다
Record it.
메모해 둬
I’ve had it, grandpa.
할아버지, 전 이미 밥을 먹고 왔어요
Record additional actions.
다른 동작까지 다 적어
I have something to say.
그럼 몇 마디만 할게요
All of you can see that
기자 분들도 보셨다시피
today's result
결과가
is a success
아주 성공적입니다
and everyone is happy about it.
모두에게 기쁜 일이죠
But
하지만 오늘
I don't want to talk about that.
제가 하고 싶은 이야기는 이게 아닙니다
Instead, what I want to say
저는 재활 과정에
is the hardships in the process.
있었던 어려움들에 관해 얘기하고 싶습니다
This patient
환자분이 작년에
had completely
중풍에 걸리면서
lost his motor skills
운동 능력을 완전히
due to a stroke last year.
상실하였는데
It put a lot of pressure
이로 인해
on him psychologically.
심리적 타격이 컸습니다
Not to mention
실험에
cooperating with the experiment,
협조하는 건 아주 힘든 결정이었어요
he even rejected
남들과 간단한 대화를
the most basic communication
나누는 것도
with others.
처음엔 거부했으니까요
But as you can see today,
하지만 오늘 보시다시피
his mood
외골격을 장착한 후
has changed dramatically
정서적으로
since being fitted
큰 변화가
with our exoskeleton.
생겼습니다
He also had
오늘
a humorous interaction
샤오위허 학생과
with Xiao Yuhe today.
유머러스하게 소통도 하셨죠
Right?
안 그래요?
That’s all.
그럼 저는 여기까지만 얘기할게요
Let’s invite Xiao Yuhe,
아래에 기술 능력이 뛰어난
the technical backbone,
샤오위허 학생이
to introduce you
기술적 문제에 대해
the technical details.
소개할 겁니다
Okay?
네
In fact,
여러분이
as you can see,
보시다시피
although grandpa hasn’t fully recovered,
할아버지는 아직 완전히 회복되지 않았지만
he can control the exoskeleton
신경 시그널로
to do some simple body movements
외골격을 통제하여
through nerve signals.
간단한 운동을 할 수 있습니다
Drinking soy milk and eating fried dough sticks
콩물도 마시고 유탸오도
is no problem for him.
먹을 수 있죠
For paralyzed patients,
사지가 마비된 환자한텐
this is something
믿기 어려운
that is unimaginable.
일이죠
Senior Xiao is so great.
샤오 선배, 너무 멋있어요
Alright.
그만해, 그만해
Your turn.
계속해서 말해 봐
The biggest technical difficulty
이번 프로젝트의
we encountered in this project
가장 큰 기술적 어려움은
was to correlate neuronal activity patterns
뉴로 활동 모델을
with motor intentions
운동 의도와 연관시켜
to form specific trigger signals.
특정 접촉 시그널을 보낼 때입니다
The process of
신호를 기반으로
controlling the required exoskeleton
외골격을 통제해야 하는데
according to the signal requires the patient
이 과정에서 환자는
to carry out certain training in the early stage.
초기에 많은 운동을 해야 합니다
Yes, because of this,
맞아요, 이것 때문에
we continued to optimize it,
끊임없이 기술을 업그레이드하였고
and finally developed
끝내
a brain-like artificial intelligence decoder.
뉴로모픽 인공지능 디코더를 개발했어요
Through virtual reality training,
가상현실을 통한 훈련으로
it has achieved
정확도가 더 높은
more accurate manipulation.
통제 효과를 얻을 수 있어요
That's why grandpa
덕분에 할아버지도
can operate so freely today.
오늘 자유롭게 움직일 수 있고요
Right.
맞아요
At present, the number of paralyzed people
현재 전 세계에서 중풍이나
caused by stroke,
뇌, 골수 손상으로 사지가
brain and spinal cord injury in the world
마비된 환자가
has reached nearly 100 million people.
약 1억 명입니다
There are 20 to 30 million
중국 내에서만
in our country,
2천에서 3천만 명이 있어요
and the data is still rising.
그리고 계속 증가하는 추세고요
In the future,
그래서 앞으로
our system and equipment
시스템과 설비들을
will be further
업그레이드시켜
iterated and updated
더 많은
to solve more
임상적인 문제를
clinical problems,
해결하려고 합니다
help patients
환자들의 행동 기능과
rebuild their behavioral
언어 능력의
and language functions,
회복을 도와
and improve their quality of life.
그들의 삶의 질을 높여줄 것입니다
As an extension of human senses,
과학기술은 인류 감각의
the value of science
연장선으로
is to give those who need it
필요한 사람한테
a promise that
보장을 제공해야 합니다
they can
더 나은 삶을 살 수
live a better life.
있다고 믿을 수 있도록
I didn't expect our major
우리 과가
to be so amazing.
이렇게 대단한 줄 몰랐네
Of course.
당연하지
Although our major is difficult,
어렵긴 해도
it is of great use.
쓸모가 많지
That’s why Xiao
그래서 샤오위허가 평소에
is usually so strict with us.
우리한테 엄격한 기준을 적용한 거야
Next time I will take you
다음엔 자폐를 앎고 있는
to see those kids with autism.
어린애들을 보러 같이 가자
They also adopted
거기 애들도
our research and development results.
우리가 연구한 기술을 사용하고 있거든
Maybe by then
그때 되면 너도
you will understand Yuhebetter.
샤오위허를 이해할 수 있을 거야
We hope to
이 분야의 연구를
continue to deepen
앞으로 더
research in this area
심화해서
and lay a solid foundation
BCI 연구를 위해
for brain-computer
튼튼한 기반을
interface research.
다지겠습니다
[Travel together on National Day]
[국경절에 같이 여행 가자]
[National Day trips]
[국경절 연휴에 여행 가자]
Hello, please take a look.
안녕하세요, 한번 보세요
Let’s go together.
우리 같이 가자
Hello.
안녕하세요
Information about National Day tours.
국경절에 여행 가고 싶지 않은가요?
Thank you.
감사합니다
Okay, thank you.
네, 감사합니다
Chengcheng.
청청
What’s your plan for National Day holiday?
국경절 연휴에 뭐 할 거야?
No idea.
아직 모르겠어
How about
아니면
the four of us
우리 넷이
go to West Sichuan together?
촨시에 가서 놀까?
Not me.
난 안 돼
I made an appointment with my senior
선배랑 쑤저우에 가서
to go to Suzhou for an academic seminar,
학술 연구하기로 했어
and I may spend
방학 내내
the whole holiday there.
거기에 있을 것 같아
Senior?
선배?
Which one?
어느 선배?
Is it the salted duck before?
저번에 말한 그 사람?
No.
아니야
He’s from the finance department.
그 선배는 금융학과고
This one is from our lab.
내가 말한 건 우리 실험실의 선배야
What an uneven distribution
우린 같이 할 사람이 없어서 못하는데
of resources. - What an uneven distribution of resources.
- 누구는 진짜 바쁘네 - 진짜 바쁘네
You are out.
그럼 넌 오지 마
Shall we three go?
우리 셋이 같이 갈까?
Not me.
나? 나는 됐어
You know me well.
우리 가족은
Every year on the National Day,
국경절 연휴마다
my family will go on a family trip
가족 여행 가는 거 너도 알잖아
to show the unity
얼마나 행복하고 화기애애한
and happiness of us.
가족 분위기인지 보여주려고
Ying.
잉 형
What about the two of us?
그럼 우리 둘이 같이 갈까?
I can’t make it, either.
나도 못 갈 것 같아
My juniors
고등학교 때
in high school
후배들이
wanted me to give them extra lessons
연휴 기간에
during the National Day holiday.
과외해 달라고 해서
I'm going to be occupied throughout the holidays.
스케줄이 꽉 찼어
It seems that I have to
그럼 국경절 연휴엔
spend the National Day holiday alone again.
나 홀로 보내야겠네
You can go home.
아니면 너도 집에 가 봐
National Day and Mid-Autumn Festival together
국경절이랑 중추절 이어서 쉬면
have eight days off.
여덟 날이잖아
It's too much trouble for me to go home.
집 가는 건 너무 번거로워
I'd better
그냥 학교에서 며칠
stay in school.
더 있을게
I haven't
마침
saved enough money
전동차 사려면 돈
for a battery cart.
모아야 해서
I will do translation to save money.
번역이나 하면서 돈벌이하지 뭐
Not bad.
괜찮은 방법이야
Good.
그것도 좋지
Hello, dad.
여보세요? 아빠
Really?
진짜?
Okay, I see.
알겠어요
My dad said he would come during the National Day holiday.
우리 아빠가 국경절에 나 보러 온대
I have something to do!
나도 할 일이 생겼다
Then all of us
그럼 우리 넷이
can hang out.
다 나가 놀 수 있겠네
Great.
좋아, 좋아
Li Meizi.
리메이쯔
[Dormitory Temptation]
[숙소의 유혹]
I'm awake. What are you doing?
나 일어났는데 너희는 뭐 하고 있어?
What is Xiao Yuhe doing
휴일인데
during the holidays?
샤오위허는 뭐 하고 있을까?
[Xiao Yuhe, what are you doing?]
[샤오위허, 뭐 해?]
Senior.
선배
Didn’t you hang out for the holiday?
연휴인데 놀러 나가지 않아요?
By the way,
참
you haven’t told me
그날 그 장난감
who taught you to make that toy.
누가 만든 건지 안 말해줬어요
Very few people know this.
그걸 만들 줄 아는 사람 별로 없는데
I learned it from a book.
책에서 본 거야
A friend of mine taught me to do it.
전 친구한테서 배운 거예요
I was surprised when you made it that day.
그날 선배가 하는 걸 보고 이상했어요
It reminded me of him.
그 친구 생각이 나서
Are you close to him?
두 사람 친해?
Yes.
친하죠
It's just that
근데 걔가 갑자기
he transferred to another school suddenly,
전학 간 바람에
and then we lost contact.
연락이 끊겼어요
Did you get in touch later?
그럼 나중에 연락 닿았어?
Later...
나중에는...
I’ll answer the call.
전화 좀 받을게요
Hello.
여보세요?
Chengcheng,
청청
I have arrived at the gate of your school.
나 지금 너희 학교 문 앞이야
So soon?
벌써요?
OK, I'll come and pick you up right away.
알겠어요, 지금 나갈게요
Senior,
선배
my father came to see me at school.
아빠가 저 보러 학교에 왔다고 해서
I have to pick him up.
마중 나가야 해요
Let’s talk about it later.
다음에 얘기해요
Musk, look.
머스크, 잘 봐
Musk.
머스크
This is for you.
이걸 너한테 선물할게
Thank you.
고마워요
Do you think
걔도
she also wanted to find me?
날 찾으려고 했을까?
Why don't you tell her
왜 당신이 주판판이라는 사실을
you are Zhu Panpan?
알리지 않았어요?
Because I'm afraid.
두려워서
Afraid of what?
뭐가 두려우세요?
[Southeast Science and Technology University]
[동남과학기술대학]
Dad.
아빠
Chengcheng.
청처
You’ve grown up.
다 큰 애가
But you are still so reckless.
이렇게 시끄러워?
Didn't you say to come on 3rd?
3일에 온다면서요?
Why didn't you tell me
왜 벌써 왔어요?
that you came in advance?
미리 말하지도 않고
Have you had lunch?
밥 드셨어요?
Su.
여보
Aunt.
아주머니
Sister.
누나
Taking advantage of the holiday,
휴일이라서
I bring your brother over to see you,
네 동생 데리고 같이 왔지
and by the way encourage him
애한테 동기부여도 해줄 겸
to get into a good school
얘도 나중에
in the future.
좋은 대학교에 진학해야 하니까
Well...
이거...
Look at me.
내가 생각이 짧았네
Hold on.
잠깐만 기다려 봐
I’ll go get another one.
하나 더 사 올게
Don’t bother, aunt.
괜찮아요, 아주머니
I usually don't drink milk tea
저 평소에 밀크티 같은 거
and the like.
잘 안 마셔요
Let's go, I'll show you around.
가요, 제가 구경시켜 줄게요
Follow your sister.
가자, 누나랑 학교 구경하러 가자
Dad.
아빠
Dad, this is the main entrance of my school.
여기가 우리 학교 정문이에요
Everyone takes a group photo here.
다들 여기서 사진을 찍는데
Those pictures you see on the Internet
평소 인터넷에서 본 사진도
are here.
다 여기서 찍은 거예요
Nice.
이쁘네
Let's take a family photo.
우리 가족 사진 한 장 찍자
Here.
자
Chengcheng, take it for us.
청청, 네가 찍어줘
Okay?
괜찮지?
Come on.
자
Ready.
준비됐어?
Three, two, one.
하나, 둘, 셋
Aunt, closer.
아주머니, 이쪽으로 서주세요
Get closer.
가깝게
-Like this. -Okay.
- 이렇게? - 네
Three, two, one. Done.
하나, 둘, 셋, 좋아요
Done?
됐지?
Let me take a look.
봐봐
Chengcheng did a good job.
청청, 진짜 잘 찍었네
Nice one.
잘 나왔네
Xuanang.
쉬안앙
Learn from your sister,
누나를 모범으로 삼아야 해
understand?
알겠어?
She’s so great to
누나 엄청 대단한 사람이야
be admitted to such a nice school.
이렇게 이쁜 대학에 진학하고
It’s pretty nice.
이쁘네
Let’s take a few pictures inside.
안에 들어가서 몇 장 더 찍을까?
Okay.
그래
There are also nice places.
안에도 이쁜 곳이 많아요
Right?
그래?
-Let’s go.
- 가요 - 가자
Go.
가자
Let’s go.
가요, 가요
He can wear these shoes
평소 운동할 때나
during sports
편하게 다닐 때
or leisure.
이걸 신으면 돼요
Quite versatile.
어떤 옷에도 잘 어울려요
So nice.
이쁘다
It’s really nice.
이쁘네
Stand up and walk around
일어나서 한번 걸어 봐
to see if it’s comfortable.
편한지
It's really pretty,
이쁘네
and it matches your outfit very well.
지금 입은 옷이랑 잘 어울려
Hello.
여기요
We want both pairs of shoes
지금 신어본 두 켤레로
we tried on.
주세요
Aunt, I have enough shoes.
아주머니, 저 신발 많아요
You don’t need to buy for me.
안 사도 돼요
Chengcheng.
청청
Your dad
너의 아버지는
likes to keep everything
뭐든
in his heart.
맘에 묻어두는 걸 좋아해
Although he doesn't often contact you,
너랑 연락을 자주 하진 않지만
he always
속으론
misses you
계속 널 생각하고
and often talks about you.
걱정하고 있어
Try to understand him,
너도 많이 이해해 줘
and don't blame him.
원망하지 말고
Aunt, I see.
아주머니, 알겠어요
I will keep in touch with my dad more often.
제가 아빠한테 자주 연락할게요
Good girl.
착하네
Nice.
이쁘다
And this.
고수 소고기 무침
Beef with cilantro.
하나 더 주세요
Okay.
네
- That’s it. - Okay.
일단 이렇게 시킬게요
Are you done picking?
다 골랐어?
Have you ordered food?
주문했어요?
Yes.
주문했어
All your favorite.
다 네가 좋아하는 걸로 주문했어
Chengcheng, what a coincidence.
청청, 이런 우연이 있네
Senior Jiafa.
자파 선배
Dad, let me introduce.
아빠, 소개할게요
This is Zhu Jiafa,
여긴 우리 실험실의
a doctoral senior in our laboratory.
박사 주자파 선배예요
Hello, uncle.
안녕하세요
-Hello. -These are my families.
- 안녕 - 여긴 우리 가족이야
- Hello. - Aunt looks so young.
- 안녕 - 정말 동안이시네요
If you didn't tell me,
난 또
I'd think she’s your sister.
네 언니인 줄 알았어
What a coincidence.
우연이네
Dad, these are the seniors
아빠, 여기도
of my laboratory.
우리 실험실의 선배들이에요
This is Xiao Yuhe.
여긴 샤오위허 선배고
This is Liu Dongmao.
여긴 류동마오 선배예요
Hello, uncle.
안녕하세요
The demands on our laboratory are high.
우리 실험실 엄청 까다로워요
I certainly wouldn't be able to stay
선배들이 저를
without them
챙겨주지 않았다면
taking care of me.
저도 오래 있지 못했을 거예요
Not at all.
아닙니다, 아닙니다
Let me invite you to lunch.
내가 밥을 살게
No need, uncle.
괜찮아요
That table is almost cleared.
저쪽에 빈자리 생긴 것 같아요
Maybe next time.
다음에 또 뵐게요
Bye, uncle.
안녕히 계세요
Here.
자, 자, 자
Chengcheng's favorite dish,
청청이 제일 좋아하는
beef with cilantro.
고수 소고기 무침이야
Chengcheng.
청청
I remember you don't eat cilantro.
너 고수 못 먹지 않아?
Right.
맞다
It is your younger brother who likes cilantro best.
쉬안앙이 제일 좋아하는 고수지
Look at me.
내 기억력 좀 봐
Come on.
자, 자
Here, chopsticks.
자, 젓가락
Chengcheng.
청청
Sorry.
미안해
Nothing.
아니에요
Let’s eat.
자, 빨리 먹어
So delicious.
맛있다
The meat looks good.
고기 신선해 보이네
Here.
자
Thank you.
고마워
Dongmao.
동마오
Your plate.
자, 먹어
[Xiao Junlan]
[샤오준란]
Hello, more seasoning.
여기요, 양념 더 주세요
Your seasoning, please.
여기요
Thank you.
고마워요
You are welcome.
아닙니다
In the past few years,
몇 년 전엔 중추절만 되면
Dr. Zhang from the School of Computer Science
컴퓨터 학과의 장 박사랑
and the three of us came here together during the Mid-Autumn Festival.
우리 셋이 같이 보냈는데
Look.
여자친구가
Since he had a girlfriend,
생긴 이후로
let alone the Mid-Autumn Festival,
중추절뿐만 아니라
we haven't seen him in any festival.
다른 명절에도 본 적이 없어
By the way, Yuhe.
참, 샤오위허
Aren’t you a local?
넌 여기 토박이 아니야?
Why do you seldom
평일에도 집에
go home?
안 갔던 것 같은데
It’s Mid-Autumn Festival today.
왜 명절에도 안 가?
My parents separated
우리 부모님은
when I was a kid.
내가 어릴 때 이혼했어
I don't like festivals,
그래서 명절 별로 안 좋아해
so I don't often come back.
집에도 잘 안 가고
I understand.
이해하지만
But it’s after all the Mid-Autumn Festival,
그래도 명절인데
you have to be with your family,
다 같이 모이면 좋잖아
right?
안 그래?
And you can talk everything
가족끼리 못 푸는
with your family.
오해는 없잖아
Right.
맞아
How about we have something to drink?
뭐 좀 마실까?
Sure.
그래
To celebrate the festival.
명절인데
What do you want?
뭐 마실래?
Mineral water.
난 생수
The same to me.
나도 생수
Waiter.
여기요
Two mineral water
생수 두 병이랑
and one iced Coke.
차가운 콜라 하나요
A signature durian mango flavour.
시그너처 두리안 망고 주스 하나랑
Okay.
네
And a Mango Sago.
망고 밀크티 하나 주세요
What do you want?
넌 뭐 마실래?
Your brother is cute, isn’t he?
동생 귀엽지?
How are you at school?
학교에선 잘 지내?
Good.
잘 지내요
Are you short of money?
돈 필요해?
Not at all.
괜찮아요
By the way,
참
are you graduating from college next year?
너 내년에 졸업하지?
I'm just a sophomore this year, dad.
아빠, 저 올해 2학년이에요
What's wrong with me today?
나 오늘 왜 이러지?
Take it to buy something you like.
이걸로 사고 싶은 거 사
Now no one gives cash.
요즘 누가 현금을 줘요?
All transfers are made online.
다 온라인으로 이체하는데
Your aunt
네 아주머니가
will check my transfer records.
내 계좌 내역을 보거든
I'm sorry for you.
아빠가 미안해
Grandpa Liu.
류 어르신
Yuhe is back.
샤오위허 왔네
Grandpa Huang.
황 어르신
Yuhe, long time no see.
샤오위허, 오랜만이야
Go ahead.
먼저 바둑 두고 계세요
Sure.
그래
Let’s continue.
자, 이어서 하자
Look at you.
너 좀 봐
Granny Guan.
관 할머니
Yuhe is back.
샤오위허 왔네
You are getting more and more handsome.
점점 더 멋있어지네
You finally learned it,
힘들게 배운 걸
but why did you forget everything
왜 시험만 치면
in the exam today?
다 잊어버리는 거야?
Yuhe is back.
샤오위허 왔네
Aunt.
이모
Can't you
위허 형 보고
learn more from Yuhe?
좀 배워
When Yuhe was young,
위허 형은 어릴 때 한 번도
his mother never worried about him.
말썽부리지 않았대
It’s okay.
괜찮아요
Step by step.
모든 건 천천히 해야죠
Mom, I’m back.
엄마, 저 왔어요
You are back.
왔어?
The meal is almost ready.
밥 거의 다 했어
I am preparing a soup.
국만 끓이면 돼
I will go back to my room.
먼저 들어가 볼게요
I made chicken soup for you.
자, 계탕이야
I didn't put any salt in it.
소금을 하나도 안 넣었어
But I think
그런데 소금 안 넣으면
it is a bit fishy without salt.
비린내가 조금 나
Let me add some soup.
엄마가 소금 넣어줄게
I don't like chicken soup with salt.
저 소금 들어간 계탕 안 좋아해요
I know.
알아
But it’s fishy
그런데 소금 안 넣으면
without salt.
비린내가 나
Add some.
조금 넣는 게 좋아
Try this.
이거 먹어 봐
Mom, where is
엄마, 우리 세 식구가 같이 찍은
our family photo?
사진 어디 갔어요?
I felt that
집에 있는
some of the furnishings in our house
가구들이
were quite old,
너무 낡아서
and they would be a nuisance,
그냥 치워버렸어
so I
괜히 눈에 거슬리잖아
threw them all away.
다 던졌어
Indeed.
낡긴 했지
But I don't feel like
그런데
a photo is a nuisance.
그 사진은 괜찮은 것 같아
And
그리고
you shouldn't deal with my items
제 동의 없이
without my permission.
제 물건을 건드리면 안 되죠
Eat first.
자, 먹어
Let’s talk after the meal.
먹고 얘기하자
I’ve had enough, mom.
전 배불러요, 엄마
Tell me
지금 말하세요
where did you throw it.
어디에 버렸어요?
What do you mean?
무슨 뜻이야?
Are you trying to get it back?
주워 오기라도 하겠다는 거야?
You care so much about your dad,
네가 그렇게 아빠를 신경 써도
but he left you at home
그 사람은 널 두고
and went abroad by himself.
혼자 해외로 떠났잖아
Think about it.
이것만 알아둬
I have been busy
어릴 때부터
working for you
널 키우느라
since you were a child,
고생한 건
raising you up.
나야
Have you
그 사진을
considered my feelings
집에 둔다고
during the years
지난 몇 년 동안...
when that photo
너...
was kept at home?
엄마가 어떤 기분일지 생각해 본 적 있어?
I have something to do in the lab.
실험실에 일이 있어서
I’m leaving.
먼저 가볼게요
Mom, what you threw away
엄마가 버린 건
was a photo of our family,
우리 가족 사진이에요
not just that of my dad.
안에 우리 아빠만 있는 건 아니에요
Chengcheng.
청청
Don’t you need me to send you back?
안 데려다줘도 돼?
No need, dad.
괜찮아요, 아빠
It is very convenient to take a taxi here,
택시 잡기도 편하고
and it is not far from the school.
학교랑도 가까워서 괜찮아요
You can get on the expressway
여기서 바로
directly from here.
고속도로로 가면 아빠도
Very convenient.
편하잖아요
I see.
알겠어
Take it, Chengcheng.
이건 네가 가져, 청청
Let’s not be like this.
여기서 이러지 마요
I’m really not short of money.
저 돈 필요하지 않아요, 정말이에요
Look, aunt bought me
봐요, 아주머니가 저한테
a lot of things already.
이렇게나 많이 사 주셨는데
That's enough for me.
이거면 됐어요
You don't have to be so embarrassed
저 때문에
because of me.
난처해할 필요 없어요
Your brother is coming.
네 동생 왔다
Here you are.
왔어?
Chengcheng.
청청
You should have a few days left
너희 휴일
on your vacation.
아직 며칠 더 있지 않아?
Don't you want to hang out with us?
우리랑 같이 놀러 가지 않을래?
It's boring
혼자 학교에 있으면
to be alone in school.
얼마나 심심해?
I’m not going, aunt.
전 괜찮아요, 아주머니
I...
저는...
Anything in school?
학교에서 할 일이 있어?
I haven’t
과제를...
finished my homework.
과제를 다 못해서요
So I want to catch up
이참에
during the holidays.
빨리 다 하려고요
Alright.
그래
That’s fine.
그럼 먼저 가볼게
Come home next time you have a holiday.
방학 때 집에 놀러 와
I'll cook something delicious for you.
아주머니가 맛있는 걸 해줄게
Okay.
네
Say goodbye to your sister.
누나랑 인사해
Bye.
갈게요
Get in the car.
자, 차에 타
Keep in touch.
그럼 전화해
Take a seat.
앉아
The bus is dangling and dangerous.
그러면 위험해
You will fall down.
넘어지겠다
-No. -Stand firm.
- 안 넘어져요 - 똑바로 서
Take a seat.
빨리 앉아
So naughty.
장난 치지 말고
I want to eat McDonald's tonight.
저녁에 맥도널드 먹고 싶어요
McDonald's again?
또 맥도널드야?
You are so fat!
이렇게 뚱뚱한데 또 먹을 거야?
Look at you.
너 지금 얼마나 뚱뚱한지 봐봐
Am I?
제가 그렇게 뚱뚱해요?
No?
아니야?
What a fatty.
이거 다 살이잖아
You…Listen.
애가 참
If you get ninety-five points in the English test,
영어 시험에서 95점 받으면
[Dad]
[아빠]
I will take you to McDonald's.
맥도널드 사줄게
Okay, deal.
약속했어요?
Deal.
그래, 약속할게
Pinky promise.
자, 깍지 걸기
You know
너도 네 엄마의
your mom well.
성격 잘 알잖아
I really worry about
널 엄마한테 보내면
you living with her.
내가 마음이 놓이지 않아
I have already processed your documents
출국 관련 서류는
for going abroad.
내가 다 준비해 뒀으니
Think about it.
잘 생각해 봐
How about going abroad with me?
아빠랑 같이 해외로 떠나지 않을래?
I have decided to stay here.
전 여기에 남아 있을 거예요
Alright.
그래
You have grown up.
너도 이젠 컸으니
I understand
다 생각이 있을 거야
you have your own ideas.
이해한다
If you encounter any difficulties in the future,
앞으로 어려움이 있으면
let me know anytime,
언제든 아빠한테 얘기해
and I will make it back to see you.
내가 어떻게든 널 보러 올게
Dad, don't worry about that.
아빠, 걱정하지 않아도 돼요
I’ve made
제가 학교에서
a good friend at school.
친구를 사귀게 되었는데
Her name is Su Chengcheng.
쑤청청이라고 해요
She is very nice to me.
걔가 나한테 엄청 잘해줘요
Whenever I meet difficulties,
제가 어려움이 있을 때마다
she will help me.
도와줬어요
Really?
그래?
You kid!
자식
Are you finally willing
이젠 친구도
to be friends with your classmates?
생긴 거야?
But you have to study hard.
공부 잘해야 해
I am leaving.
아빠는 먼저 가볼게
I bought you
저번에 너한테
a new mobile phone.
전화 사줬잖아
Remember to call me.
전화하는 거 잊지 마
Okay.
네
Chengcheng doesn't like cilantro.
청청은 고수를 안 좋아하니까
Dad will help you pick up
앞으로 아빠가 고수를
all the cilantro,
다 빼줄게
okay?
어때?
Okay!
좋아
Smile.
자, 웃어 봐
What are you doing?
어디 가는 거야?
Hold on.
거기 서
I'm going to see Chengcheng.
청청 보러 갈 거야
It’s late. Don’t go in.
지금 몇 시인데, 들어가지 마
Look at you.
진짜
Why are you so drunk every day?
왜 술을 이렇게 많이 마신 거야?
Just take a look.
한 번만 볼게
What are you doing, Su Zhiqiang?
뭐 하는 거야? 쑤쯔창
Chengcheng.
청청
My good girl.
우리 착한 딸
She looks so much like me.
나랑 똑 닮았네
My baby!
우리 공주님
Enough.
그만해
Leave.
저리 가요
Get out.
나가
No way.
안 돼
What else do you want?
또 뭘 하려고?
I’m giving a present to my daughter.
우리 딸한테 줄 선물이 있어
Get out.
나가
Her favorite.
청청이 제일 즐겨 먹는 거야
Chengcheng, I love you.
청청, 아빠가 많이 사랑해
I love you.
아빠가 많이 사랑해
Chengcheng.
청청
Enough.
그만해
Leave.
빨리 나가
Look at you.
아니
Get out.
나가
Chengcheng, I love you.
청청, 아빠가 많이 사랑해